A Finding Aid to the Joseph F. McCrindle Papers, 1877-2013, in the Archives of American Art AAA.mccrjose
Archives of American Art
Joseph F. McCrindle papers
1877-2013
AAA.mccrjose
Archives of American Art
5.3 Linear feet
The papers of New York art collector and philanthropist, Joseph F. McCrindle, measure 5.3 linear feet and date from 1877-2013. The collection documents McCrindle's art collecting, art donations, philanthropy, family affairs, and personal estate. Found are extensive art inventories, sales receipts, gift and loan documentation, and photographs of artwork. The papers also include Joseph McCrindle's estate records and wills, family papers, records from the Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation, correspondence with museums and galleries, and photographs of McCrindle and family members.
McCrindle, Joseph F.
Biographical/Historical note
Lifelong resident of New York City, Joseph Feder McCrindle (1923-2008) was a collector, art patron, publisher, and philanthropist. He founded the Transatlantic Review and The Henfield Foundation.
Born to John Ronald McCrindle and Odette Feder McCrindle on March 27, 1923, Joseph McCrindle was exposed to art appreciation at an early age. After his parents were divorced in 1924 and his mother remarried in 1928, he was raised primarily by his grandparents, Joseph F. Feder and Edith Mosler Feder. Summers were spent abroad in Europe, courtesy of the family yacht, where he developed his knowledge of art history and studied foreign languages.
McCrindle attended the St. Paul's School in Manhattan, followed by Harvard University, graduating in 1944. During World War II, McCrindle served with the Office of Strategic Services in London, where he attained the rank of first lieutenant. He went on to receive a law degree from Yale University in 1948.
After working briefly in the publishing world, McCrindle became a literary agent. In 1959, he started the Transatlantic Review, a London-based literary journal. He remained in place as editor and publisher until the company closed in 1977.
The Henfield Foundation, now known as the Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation, was established by McCrindle in 1958 to provide grants to organizations focused on the development of art, music, and social justice.
Joseph McCrindle was a notable art collector and donated and loaned many works of art to museums and galleries. McCrindle amassed 2,500 old master drawings in his lifetime, in addition to Italian baroque paintings, 19th-century drawings, British artwork, and more. Some examples of gifts and loans documented in the McCrindle papers include an extended a loan of John Singer Sargent's Landscape With Two Women in Foreground to the Yale Center for British Art in 1982, Salvator Rosa's The Torment of Tityus to the Museum and Art Gallery of Stanford University in 1992, and Luca Giordano's Saint Barnabas to the Fine Arts Museum of San Francisco in 2002.
Joseph McCrindle died on July 11, 2008. His collection was bequeathed to a number of institutions across the nation, such as the Brooklyn Museum, the National Gallery of Art, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Joseph F. McCrindle papers were donated in 2012-2013 by Joseph F. McCrindle via John Rowe, president and CEO of the Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2014 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website. Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation records and printed material have not been digitized.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of New York art collector and philanthropist, Joseph F. McCrindle, measure 5.3 linear feet and date from 1877-2013. The collection documents McCrindle's art collecting, art donations, philanthropy, family affairs, and personal estate. Found are extensive art inventories, sales receipts, gift and loan documentation, and photographs of artwork. The papers also include Joseph McCrindle's estate records and wills, family papers, records from the Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation, correspondence with museums and galleries, and photographs of McCrindle and family members.
Biographical and family materials include McCrindle's obituary, copies of printed programs from his memorial service, and legal documents dealing with his will. There are papers dealing with his grandparents, Joseph Fuller Feder and Edith Mosler Feder, his mother, Odette Feder Moffett, and blueprints and paperwork for his grandfather's yacht, the M.Y. Kihna.
Materials from the Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation include the certificate of incorporation for the Henfield Foundation, change of name documentation to rename it the Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation, by-laws for the organization, waiver notices for special called meetings, minutes for annual and special meetings, financial statements, and gift lists. McCrindle corresponded heavily with various museums and galleries. Also found are letters from family, friends, and colleagues, such as Michael Levey, Brian Sewell, and Pinckney Benedict. Legal correspondence concerns McCrindle's estate. Sympathy and condolences are addressed to John Rowe on the occasion of Joseph McCrindle's death.
Personal business records concern McCrindle's art collection, sales, bequests, and his estate. The art collection is documented in extensive art inventories and lists, most of which is found in two large dismantled notebooks. Sales receipts are also found for McCrindles purchases as early as 1942. There are artwork appraisals, and documentation of McCrindle's gifts and loans of artwork to museums and galleries. There are early receipts and invoices for rare books, decorative items, antiques, and artwork purchases by Joseph and Edith Feder, McCrindle's grandparents.
Printed material includes a copy of the text, Old Master Drawings from the Collection of Joseph F. McCrindle, donor reports, exhibition catalogs, clippings, assorted bulletins and newsletters, and programs from live performances.
Loose photographs are of Joseph McCrindle, from early childhood through adulthood. There are also photographs of his family, including his grandparents, Joseph and Edith Feder, his mother, Odette Feder Moffett, and his half brother, Antoine DuBourg. There are photo albums containing images of McCrindle as a child; of his mother as a child; family and travel photographs; and photographs taken during cruises on the family yacht, M.Y. Kihna. Three of the albums are dedicated to Kihna travels.
Related Archival Materials note
The bulk of Joseph F. McCrindle's papers are housed at Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into six series:
Series 1: Biographical and Family Material, 1913-2008 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1, OV 9)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1946-2012 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, circa 1919-2010 (2.0 linear feet; Box 1-3)
Series 4: Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation Records, 1958-2012 (0.3 linear feet; Box 3)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1899-2013 (0.4 linear feet; Box 4)
Series 6: Photographic Material, 1877-2006 (1.8 linear feet; Box 4-6)
Benedict, Pinckney, 1964-; DuBourg, Antoine; Feder, Edith Mosler; Feder, Joseph Fuller; Henfield Foundation.; Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation.; Levey, Michael; Lowe, John; Moffett, Odette Feder; Sewell, Brian; Art--Collectors and collecting--New York (State)--New York; Blueprints; Philanthropists--New York (State)--New York; Photographs
- Biographical and Family Material, 1913-2008; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1, OV 9
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes McCrindle's obituary, copies of printed programs from his memorial service, and revisions of his will, as well as memorandums and codicils to his will. Dana W. Hiscock and John T. Rowe were executors of McCrindle's estate and appear frequently in the records.
  Also found here are family papers. Papers of his grandfather, Joseph Fuller Feder, primarily concern the design and building of his yacht, the M.Y. Kihna, including blueprints. Papers of McCrindle's grandmother, Edith Mosler Feder, include receipts and correspondence centered on the furnishing and upkeep of her home, a copy of her will, a 1933 patent for a clasp, and estate records. McCrindle's mother married three times, and material is found under her maiden name of Odette Feder, as well as her married names: Odette McCrindle, Odette du Bourg de Bozas, and Odette Moffett. Papers of interest include a copy of divorce records from her first marriage, the marriage certificate from her second marriage, and estate and trust fund documentation. Other family frecords include cemetery cards for family members and a map of Woodlawn Cemetery.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  This series has been digitized in its entirety.
  - Joseph F. McCrindle Obituaries and Memorial Program, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Joseph F. McCrindle Draft Copies of Will, 1991-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
  - Joseph F. McCrindle Codicil to Will, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Joseph F. McCrindle Schematic of Dispositions of Will, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Joseph F. McCrindle Memorandums to Will, 2008; 2004 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Joseph F. Feder Papers, 1913-1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Edith M. Feder Papers, 1913-1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Edith M. Feder Will, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Estate of Edith M. Feder Affidavit of Appraisal, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Edith M. Feder Inventory of Chattels, circa 1925 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Edith M. Feder Establishment of Trust Fund, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Edith M. Feder Patent, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Edith M. Feder Sale of Furnishings, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Odette F. Moffett Papers, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Odette F. McCrindle Divorce Papers, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Odette F. Moffett Estate Settlement, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Odette F. Moffett Judicial Settlement of Estate, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Odette F. Moffett Trust Fund Papers, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Burials and Cemeteries, 1960-1966; 2009; 1927 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Oversized items housed in OV 9.
  - Motor Yacht Kihna, 1929-1936 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Oversize Yacht Blueprints, S.S. Berengaria Map, and Woodlawn Cemetery Map, 1927-1930 (Box OV 9)
    Oversized items scanned with Box 1, Folders 25-26.
- Correspondence, 1946-2012; Series 2; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence with museums and galleries is the largest category within this series. Individual institutions with which McCrindle or representatives of his estate corresponded include Adelson Galleries, The Brooklyn Museum of Art, Duke University Museum of Art, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, The Minneapolis Institute of Arts, The Morgan Library and Museum, The National Gallery of Art, Philadelphia Museum of Art, The Art Museum of Princeton University, Rutgers University Art Gallery, Smithsonian Institution Museums and Galleries, Yale University Art Gallery, and The Jane Vorhees Zimmerli Art Museum. Other museums and galleries that did not have a large volume of correspondence are housed in a separate folder.
  Also found is correspondence with family, friends, and colleagues, such as Michael Levey, Brian Sewell, and Pinckney Benedict. Correspondence from the law firm, Patterson, Belknap, Webb, and Tyler, deals with McCrindle's will and the bequeathal of his artwork. Sympathy and condolences are addressed to John Rowe on the occasion of Joseph McCrindle's death. Email conversations between John Rowe and Jason Kaufman and between Rowe and Richard Ormond are also in this series.
  - Adelson Galleries, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Brooklyn Museum of Art, 1960-1996 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Duke University Museum of Art, 1996-2001 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1960-1991 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Minneapolis Institute of Arts, 1964-2010 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Morgan Library and Museum, 2007-2010 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - National Gallery of Art, 1991-2011 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Art Museum of Princeton University, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Rutgers University Art Gallery, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Smithsonian Institution Museums and Galleries, 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Yale University Art Gallery, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Zimmerli Art Museum, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Other Museums and Galleries, 1960-2012 (Box 1, Folder 40-41)
  - Family, Friends, and Colleagues, 1946-2009 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Legal Correspondence, 1961-2009 (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
  - Sympathy and Condolences on the Death of Joseph F. McCrindle, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1919-2010; Series 3; 2 Linear feet Box 1-3
  Found are assorted lists, forms, and other paperwork. Records associated with McCrindle's estate, lists of bequests, sales invoices, and art collection inventories are among the bulk of the materials. Early receipts and invoices are from rare books, decorative items, antiques, and artwork purchases by Joseph and Edith Feder, McCrindle's grandparents. Also found in this series are appraisals of McCrindle's artwork and paperwork dealing with gifts and loans from his collection to museums and galleries. Appraisal companies of note are Christie's and Sotheby's, both auction houses. This series includes the contents of at least two dismantled notebooks, which include lists, inventories, and other records of his artwork donations. Some records were created by John Rowe, either as a representative for the Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation, or as an executor of McCrindle's estate.
  The bulk of this series has been digitized. Certain documents containing financial information have not been digitized.
  - Estate Appraisal of Printed Books, Manuscripts, Autograph Letters and Literary Drawings, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Joseph F. McCrindle Settlement of Estate, 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Joseph F. McCrindle Bequests, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Joseph F. McCrindle Partial Release of Power of Appointment, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Joseph F. McCrindle Other Estate Records, 1944-1960 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Gifts and Loans, 1953-2009 (Box 1, Folder 51-55)
  - Consignments, 1975-2000 (Box 1, Folder 56-58)
  - Shipping Receipts, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 59-61)
  - Sales Receipts and Invoices, circa 1919-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Sales Receipts and Invoices, 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7-12)
  - Sales Receipts and Invoices, 1977-1997 (Box 2, Folder 13-20)
  - Gift Property of Joseph F. McCrindle, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Inventories, circa 1976-2010 (Box 2, Folder 22-30)
  - Museum Shipping Lists, circa 2010 (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
  - Appraisals and Valuations, 1960-2001 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Valuation for Sale at Auction in London of Furniture, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Valuation for Insurance of Pictures and Drawings, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 28-30)
  - Insurance Appraisal, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - Christie's Estate Tax Appraisals, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 33-35)
  - Christie's Estate Tax Appraisals, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Appraisals, New York Appraisal Corporation, 1973-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Soetheby's Valuation, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Notebook, Records on Art Work, 2007-2008 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
  - Notebook, Joseph F. McCrindle Collection Worklist, undated (Box 3, Folder 7-11)
  - Notebook, Joseph F. McCrindle Collection Inventory List, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Notebook, Joseph F. McCrindle Collection Inventory List, Annotated, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Notebook, McCrindle Inventory, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Notebook, Gifts, 1961-2008 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Notebook, Joseph F. McCrindle Collection Checklist, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Price Lists, 1961-2009 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation Records, 1958-2012; Series 4; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3
  Materials from the Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation include the certificate of incorporation for The Henfield Foundation, change of name documentation to rename as the Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation, by-laws for the organization, waiver notices for special called meetings, minutes for annual and special meetings, financial statements, and gift lists. The Foundation was established in 1958 under the name, The Henfield Foundation. In March 2005, the name was changed to the Joseph F. McCrindle Foundation.
  This series has not been digitized.
  - Founding Documents, 2005; 1958 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Waivers of Notice, Minutes, and Agendas, 1958-2012 (Box 3, Folder 19-32)
  - Financial Records, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Audited Balance Sheets, June 2006-June 2007 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Gifts, 2008; 1981 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Other Documents, 2000-2007 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Fund Agreements, 2011-2012 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Printed Material, 1899-2013; Series 5; 0.4 Linear feet Box 4
  Printed material consists of a copy of the text, Old Master Drawings from the Collection of Joseph F. McCrindle, exhibition catalogs, assorted bulletins and newsletters, and programs from live performances. Articles and clippings includes an announcement of his grandparents' marriage, a clipping on the portrait of his grandmother, Edith Mosler Feder, by her father, painter Henry Mosler, and a clipping featuring his mother, Odette Feder Moffett, at the time she was married to Guy Du Bourg de Bozas. Other materials include institutional donor reports, internet printouts about artwork, assorted lists, business cards, and a copy of the text, The Henfield Prize Stories.
  - Catalogs, 1926-2011 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Old Master Drawings from the Collection of Joseph F. McCrindle, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bulletins and Newsletters, 1963-2013 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Reports, 1972-2013 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Articles and Clippings, 1899-2012 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Playbills and Programs, 2012-2013 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Internet Printouts, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Lists, Notes, and Business Cards, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Henfield Prize Stories, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Photographic Material, 1877-2006; Series 6; 1.8 Linear feet Box 4-8
  Photographs of Joseph McCrindle range from early childhood to older adulthood. There are also photographs of his family, including his grandparents, Joseph Feder and Edith Mosler Feder, photographs of his mother, Odette Feder Moffett, and other individuals. In addition to the loose photographs, there are photo albums and photographs in mats. The photo albums consist of pictures of McCrindle as a child, pictures of his mother, Odette Feder Moffett, as a child, pictures of McCrindle and his half brother, Antoine du Bourg de Bozas, family and travel photographs, photographs of his grandparents, and photographs taken during cruises on the Kihna. There are three albums dedicated to the Kihna travels. Also included among the photographs was an annotated typewritten address list belonging to Mrs. George Moffett (Odette Feder Moffett). Located inside the folded list was a small vinatge photograph of Antoine Dubourg, Jospeh McCrindle's younger brother.
  This series has been digitized in its entirety except for slides.
  - Joseph F. McCrindle, circa 1926-circa 1975 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Family, 1877-1956 (Box 4, Folder 13-17)
    Oversized items housed in Box 8, Folder 3.
  - Other People and Places, circa 1940-1990s (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Found are photographs of British Prime Minister Neville Camberlain, Peter Brown, Frederick den Broeder, John Rowe and others. Also found are photographs of McCrindle's properties in San Juan, Puerto Rico and Charleston, South Carolina.
  - Mrs. George M. Moffett Address List and Photograph, circa 1928 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Travel, circa 1920s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Decorative Objects and Furnishings, circa 1930s-2006 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Included are photographs of the interior of homes belonging to Odette Feder Moffett and Edith Mosler Feder.
  - Joseph F. McCrindle Art Collection, 1966-2000 (Box 4, Folder 23-27)
  - Joseph F. McCrindle Art Collection, 1966-2000 (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
  - Slides, circa 1971 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Included are slides of artwork and the interior of homes belonging to Odette Feder Moffett and Edith Mosler Feder.
  - Photograph Album, Joseph F. McCrindle Second Birthday Party, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Photograph Album, "Cruise of Summer 1934" (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photograph Album, "The Cruise of the Kihna, Pt. I", 1935 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photograph Album, "The Cruise of the Kihna, Pt. II", 1935 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photograph Album, Family and Travel, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    The dismantled album contains photographs of Joseph McCrindle and family members, as well as photographs of buildings, scenery, and seascapes.
  - Photograph Album, Odette Feder Moffett Childhood Photographs, 1901-1911 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Album with enscription, "To my grandson Joseph McCrindle from Didi, April 1935."
  - Photograph Album, "M.Y. Kihna, August 1938", 1938 August (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Oversize Family Photographs, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Oversized items scanned with Box 4, Folder 17.